<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>HelenaJamborWrites</title>
<link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/</link>
<atom:link href="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Blog about data visualization and visual communication of scientific data</description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.552</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>How to… Poster Design</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Poster24/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="poster-preparation-the-ultimate-list-of-resources" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="poster-preparation-the-ultimate-list-of-resources">Poster preparation: The ultimate list of resources</h4>
<p>With the pandemic over for good, we are truly back to in-person conferences and their packed poster sessions. Think about the numbers: each year, well over hundred thousand poster are presented at academic and industry networking events. Think about the effort: each poster is made in many hours spent trying to concisely communicate a message. Think about the room for improvements: many of the posters are densely filled with text and fail to spark joy. Here are a few tipps for tools and visuals for better posters in 2024:</p>
</section>
<section id="tools-for-poster-preparation" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tools-for-poster-preparation">Tools for poster preparation</h4>
<p>In 2024 numerous tools exist that help scientists prepare electronic posters for conferences. Common are software for designing slides, vector-design software, and webbased applications. Vector design software allow for zooming of visualizations without quality loss – meaning not pixelation will suddenly appear when a poster designed on small screen is printed at life size. Here is a roundup of some useful ones:</p>
<section id="open-source-software" class="level6">
<h6 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="open-source-software">Open source software</h6>
<ul>
<li>Inkscape: A free vector graphic software that is rapidly being developed and becoming more usable every day. In Inkscape you can directly import of icons from icon libraries, e.g., when needing symbols. Inkscape also permits scripting: images can be processed with ImageJ and data can be visualized with R inside Inkscape. Plus, a practical guide for biologists exists (Cvrčková, 2019).</li>
<li>ImageJ: An open-source image processing software, offers extensive possibilities for image processing. For layouting of posters primarily composed of images, software extensions (“plugins”) can be used, e.g., ScientiFig or FigureJ. Both plugins allow users to arrange multiple images, graphs, and annotations into a single composite figure and has tools for aligning, resizing, and labeling images.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="software" class="level6">
<h6 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="software">Software</h6>
<ul>
<li>Adobe Illustrator / Affinity Designer / CorelDraw: The proprietary alternatives to Inkscape. Adobe Illustrator is widely used and tutorials help new users along (Culley, 2016).</li>
<li>PowerPoint / Keynote: Often PowerPoint will produce posters of sufficient quality, especially when the canvas size is adjusted and slides are exported as vector graphics such as PDF. When saving your graphical abstract check the settings to make sure that your images are not compressed to prevent pixelation artifacts.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="web-based" class="level6">
<h6 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="web-based">Web-based</h6>
<ul>
<li>Flourish: online data visualization tool that allows users to create visually appealing charts – which can be combined into data-driven posters. Flourish has numerous customizable templates for common but also uncommon charts. Plus, can handle relatively large datasets.</li>
<li>Figma: is mostly used for prototyping in design, but I have come across many people that use it also use it for poster design. A plus, it allows collaborative work and graphic editing, and the outputs are vector graphic designs. Especially for collaborative work and prototyping Figma can be integrated with a number of other tools, e.g.&nbsp;SLACK, Adobe Cloud, Confluence, Dropbox etc.</li>
<li>Canva: used for designing visuals for many purposes, popular for its user-friendly interface. Includes a number of templates, a built-in icon and photo library, and also permits real-time collaboration. It is possible to upload contents, such as microscopy image, charts, or user icons, such as the logo of your institute or funder.</li>
<li>BioRender: proprietary web-based software with a very large biomedical icon library, whose appearance, shape, color, and detail, cannot be changed. A drawback to many labs is also BioRender’s continuous adaptation of licenses, while an advantage is the its interface with public databases, such as the Protein Data Bank.</li>
<li>MindtheGraph: MindtheGraph is an online platform designed to help users create scientifically accurate and visually appealing illustrations, particularly for academic and research purposes. It offers a Also includes a library of pre-made scientific illustrations and templates. User-friedly drag and drop, and collaborative mode are possible.</li>
</ul>
<p>For a more thorough review of common software and their advantages/disadvantages:</p>
<ul>
<li>Martin, K., 2020. A picture is worth a thousand words. MEW 29, 28–34.</li>
<li>Perkel, J.M., 2020. The software that powers scientific illustration. Nature 582, 137–138. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-020-01404-7">see paper</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="catchy-visuals" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="catchy-visuals">Catchy visuals</h4>
<p>The first thing most audiences see from afar are key visuals. These can be large picures, charts, icons, or a simple graphical abstract. Some posters even are entirely visual, presenting data in a story format e.g.&nbsp;as a comic strip. In particular icons and symbols, which we learn early and thus understand almost intuitively, work well when we want to rapidly grab attention. Icons can even replace or support text, e.g.&nbsp;in titles, legends, or axis labels. Today, we have a vast number or open access resources at our fingertips, and the collection of free icon is expanding daily. Most resources contain icons in either adaptable format (“SVG”) or as image (“PNG”), or both.</p>
<section id="general-icons" class="level6">
<h6 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="general-icons">General icons:</h6>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://fontawesome.com">Fontawesome</a> is a Unicode-based icon library that can be installed locally as a font for graphic programs, downloaded as full icon library, or downloaded as individual SVG images.</li>
<li><a href="https://thenounproject.com">Nounproject</a> a collection of icons from various designers. Hence, the available icons are vast, but also not matched in style. These icons can be used after registration for free with attribution as SVG or PNG.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.svgrepo.com">SVGrepo</a> currently largest SVG icon library, icons are searchable by style.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.flaticon.com/">Flaticon</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="biology-medicine-icons" class="level6">
<h6 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="biology-medicine-icons">Biology &amp; Medicine icons</h6>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.phylopic.org/">Phylopic</a> offers shapes of numerous animals, plants and further model organisms, e.g.&nbsp;for phylogenetic trees.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/style-lab/general/fonts/v1.3/">EBI icon library</a> provides some general scientific icons.</li>
<li><a href="https://reactome.org/icon-lib">Reactome</a> provides scientific pictograms and chemical drawings for free re-use and encourages the upload of user-designed pictograms for sharing with the scientific community.</li>
<li><a href="https://smart.servier.com/">Smart</a> is a free collection of medical drawings from Servier Medical Art and can be downloaded as a full slide-deck and used with attribution.</li>
<li><a href="https://bioicons.com/">Bioicons</a> is an expanding set of biology and laboratory icons from petri dishes to model organisms available under free licenses (CC0). Initially by Servier, the drawings are expanded with user provided samples.</li>
<li><a href="https://healthicons.org/">Health Icons</a> is a global volunteer effort to create common icons for many specialized medical scenarios available under creative commons license (CC0).</li>
<li><a href="https://scidraw.io/">SciDraw</a> is a repository of free SVG cartoons for science supported by the Sainsbury Wellcome Centre, UK</li>
<li><a href="https://healthicons.org/">Healthicons</a> offer many icons specifically dedicated to medical procedures, diagnoses, and eqipment that is not often included in regular icon libraries.</li>
</ul>
<p>For inspiration check out the first icon library, designed by Gerd Arntz for the Isotype project in the early 1900s. Despite Otto Neurath and Gerd Arntz intending the isotype project as a common worldwide visual language, their relatives decided to hold copyright <a href="http://www.gerdarntz.org/isotype.html">link</a>.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="understandable-title-and-text" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="understandable-title-and-text">Understandable title and text</h4>
<p>The number of words that Bernard Brown showed on his poster about poster design is 131 – and he hints to the fact that this may be enough for academic conference posters. Thus, concise writing is essential for posters.</p>
<div class="{fig-brown}">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Poster24/Brown_Poster.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Brown - producing punchy posters</p>
</div>
<p>But the first impression of a poster comes from a title – if this is cluttered with abbreviations clear to you and your labmates but not the wider attendees, they might not dare to stop. But even the title should also be short and there is science to support this. Letford et al analysed 20,000 papers and showed that the shorter the title, the more citations a paper received. This may be multiple factors, but one aspect is that shorter titles are easier to understand.</p>
<div class="{fig-titles}">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Poster24/titles.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The advantage of short paper titles, figure from letchford 2015.</p>
</div>
</section>
<section id="catchy-colorschemes" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="catchy-colorschemes">Catchy Colorschemes</h4>
<p>The industrial designer Henry Dreyfuss is cited saying that “colours are the exclamation marks in design” – color perception is immediate and we cannot ignore colors. Colors should be used 1. To focus the attention, by applying color where readers should look first; 2. Consistently, colorschemes should not change from one panel to the next if they have the same meaning; 3. Accessible to all audiences, i.e., colors should have high contrast to background and be visible to colorblind.</p>
<section id="tools-for-colors" class="level6">
<h6 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tools-for-colors">Tools for Colors:</h6>
<ul>
<li>Test accessibility of your colours, e.g., by rendering your display (iOS: accessibility&gt;display&gt;colorfilters) or by uploading a screenshot of the poster to a <a href="http://www.color-blindness.com/coblis-color-blindness-simulator/">web-tool</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://webaim.org/resources/contrastchecker/">Check color contrast:</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.colourblindawareness.org/">Color blind friendly?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://colorbrewer2.org">Pick colors for data</a></li>
<li><a href="https://projects.susielu.com/viz-palette">Test if colors work with charts</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="design-a-color-scheme" class="level6">
<h6 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="design-a-color-scheme">Design a color scheme:</h6>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://paletton.com">paletton</a></li>
<li><a href="https://color.adobe.com/create/color-wheel">Adobe color</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pick-color-from-image" class="level6">
<h6 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pick-color-from-image">Pick color from image:</h6>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://icolorpalette.com/color-palette-from-images">Icolorpalette</a></li>
<li><a href="https://hexcolor.co/image-to-colors#">hexcolor</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="new-poster-formats" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-poster-formats">New poster formats</h4>
<p>A lasting effect from COVID times is that conference formats have forever become more diverse. Hybrid conferences are here to stay to accommodate various reasons for virtual attendance, from care work at home, limited travel budgets, or problems getting visa’s. Hybrid conferences have not only online or hybrid poster sessions, but often also poster flash talks or online-only rooms for mingling, e.g.&nbsp;in gather town. This diversity requires more preparation – the poster flash talk needs one easy and pretty slide with the key information, the digital poster usually is smaller than its print counterpart, and the online-room require an extra level of confidence.</p>
</section>
<section id="prepare" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="prepare">Prepare!</h4>
<p>And last, get feedback on the poster before print and have a short “Elevator pitch” ready. You may only have one minute to grab the attention of someone in the coffee line, rushing past your poster, so a ready-to-fire run-down of the main points is essential. For feeedback, get your colleaagues to speficifcally comment on the readability of poster text and figures. It turns out that most poster presenters do not receive feedback before hitting the print button <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fbinf.2023.1216139">See paper</a>. Two questions you may ask: 1. What do you see first? This ideally is the title and the key visual, if not revise. 2. Ask someone to explain the poster back to you. When they get stuck it usually is because something is not quite clear. You can also use this silly “Bad Poster Bingo” to make sure your poster does not disappoint.</p>
<div class="{fig-bingo}">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Poster24/bingo.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Enjoy a game of bad poster bingo - or check it to avoid common mistakes. Get a printable version: https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.26012899.v2</p>
</div>
</section>
<section id="a-number-of-guides-introduce-life-scientists-to-poster-design" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-number-of-guides-introduce-life-scientists-to-poster-design">A number of guides introduce life scientists to poster design:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Barker, E., Phillips, V., 2021. Creating conference posters: Structure, form and content. J Perioper Pract 31, 296–299. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1750458921996254">See paper</a></li>
<li>Block, S.M., 1996. Do’s and don’t’s of poster presentation. Biophysical Journal 71, 3527–3529. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0006-3495(96)79549-8">See paper</a></li>
<li>Boullata, J.I., Mancuso, C.E., 2007. A “How-To” Guide in Preparing Abstracts and Poster Presentations. Nutr Clin Pract 22, 641–646. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0115426507022006641">See paper</a></li>
<li>Brown, B.S., 1997. Poster design—Six points to ponder. Biochemical Education 25, 136–137. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0307-4412(97)00045-9">See paper</a></li>
<li>Brown, B.S., 1996. Communicate your science! … Producing punchy posters. Trends Cell Biol 6, 37–39. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0962-8924(96)81037-3">See paper</a></li>
<li>Erren, T.C., Bourne, P.E., 2007. Ten simple rules for a good poster presentation. PLoS Comput Biol 3, e102. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030102">See paper</a></li>
<li>Faulkes, Z., 2021. Better Posters: Plan, Design and Present an Academic Poster. Pelagic Publishing Ltd.</li>
<li>Fraser, J., Fuller, L., Hutber, G., 2016. Creating Effective Conference Abstracts and Posters in Biomedicine: 500 Tips for Success. CRC Press.</li>
<li>Jambor, H.K., 2023. Insights on poster preparation practices in life sciences. Front Bioinform 3, 1216139. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fbinf.2023.1216139">See paper</a></li>
<li>Wang, A., Greda, D., Carroll, S., Bianchi, L.M., Cunningham, C.D., 2022. Preparing and Giving Effective Poster Presentations, in: Research During Medical Residency. CRC Press.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>datavis</category>
  <category>PosterDesign</category>
  <category>how-to</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Poster24/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Poster24/bingo.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="161" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Win the Poster Prize</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Poster_2020/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="win-the-poster-prize-or-at-least-produce-nice-posters-while-trying" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="win-the-poster-prize-or-at-least-produce-nice-posters-while-trying">Win the Poster Prize (Or, at least, produce nice posters while trying)</h4>
<p>Students on average author 1-3 papers and produce at least three times that many conference posters (<a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fbinf.2023.1216139">see our study</a>). At large meetings, such as the ASCB, thousands of posters are presented each year. While presenting posters is popular, posters sessions evoke mixed feelings: they are often late in the evening, interrupted by special workshops, held in badly lit rooms far away from the bar, and many posters are subpar: they are crammed with details and text in small font, and presenters elaborate in great detail. Experienced conference attendees therefore excel in the brief scanning of the title while avoiding eye contact with the presenter for fear of being entangled in a never-ending run-down of experimental details.</p>
<p>While we can’t influence the conference organization, we can absolutely and with little effort improve the posters! Based on my survey data, I compiled the top ten tips to improve your poster:</p>
</section>
<section id="legible-title" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="legible-title">Legible title</h4>
<p>Make the title and your name readable from afar. This means, not too many words per title, maybe 6 to 10, in a legible font – Helvetica Neue, Verdana, Calibri or similar. Refrain also from ALL CAPS as it becomes hard to read after a few words. If you love all caps, why not try Small Caps with capitalization instead.</p>
</section>
<section id="avoid-abbreviations" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="avoid-abbreviations">Avoid abbreviations</h4>
<p>Ideally no abbreviations in the title and as few as possible in the poster content. Only few abbreviations are so common that they became words themselves: DNA, RNA, some gene and protein names. You don’t want to turn audience away with jargon, and remember, even specialist’s conferences are attended by editors, journalists, and newcomers in the field – be welcoming to them all!</p>
</section>
<section id="not-too-much-text" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="not-too-much-text">Not too much text</h4>
<p>We read maximally 100-200 words per minute – but in posters, with scientific data, terms, and charts our reading speed will be significantly decreased. Keep that in mind – I personally am more convinced by a figure than by you explaining and interpreting it.</p>
</section>
<section id="clear-section-layout" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="clear-section-layout">Clear section layout</h4>
<p>Start at the top left and end at the bottom right. This is how we read text, and also posters! Alternative: arrange your content in 2-3 columns, similar to an article – make sure the columns are clear by leaving enough white space surrounding them! Please refrain from unconventional layouts – the chances are high that it will confuse your readers!</p>
<div class="{fig-1}">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Poster_2020/layout_normal.png" class="img-fluid"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Poster_2020/layout_colums.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Organization and layout is key: commit to one reading direction and then stick to either column or row layout.</p>
</div>
</section>
<section id="figure-titles-instead-of-legends" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="figure-titles-instead-of-legends">Figure titles instead of legends</h4>
<p>This is easy – try moving the figure legend above the image/chart, instead of showing it below as you would in a paper. Right away, this gives you a header for that section! Explanations of the color code, which are critical to understand a figure, can be sub-headers!</p>
<div class="{fig-titles}">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Poster_2020/legend_to_title-01.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Increase legibility with figure titles instead of figure legends!</p>
</div>
</section>
<section id="consistent-color-code" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="consistent-color-code">Consistent color code</h4>
<p>Absolutely keep the color code consistent across all figures! Nothing kills more time than figuring out the color code of each individual chart! Please, if your main experiment/mutant/condition is shown in “red” in the first figure, do not deviate from this in the next figure! And, of course, be color-blind friendly (no mixing red and green!)</p>
<div class="{fig-color}">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Poster_2020/color_code.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Pick a consistent color scheme. Experiment in red, control in blue? Do not use these colors for anything else.</p>
</div>
</section>
<section id="simple-pictures-and-charts." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="simple-pictures-and-charts.">Simple pictures and charts.</h4>
<p>There is likely fascinating detail in your data, but not everyone wants to know all of it during a poster session. Therefore, please consider removing unnecessary details from your graphs! (Also: avoid 3D, no bar charts for distributions (#BarBarCharts) and avoid unconventional graph-types: it’s already unlikely people understand them in a paper, and less likely they feel like deciphering them in a poster session.</p>
</section>
<section id="poster-etiquette-have-the-elevator-pitch-ready" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="poster-etiquette-have-the-elevator-pitch-ready">Poster-Etiquette: Have the elevator pitch ready!</h4>
<p>Give your audience a polite overview in 2-3 minutes that includes the big picture and key finding, but leave out experimental details. If they are interested in more, they will ask! (Also, it is convenient to have this 2-minute blurb ready in case you accidentally bump into the heroine/hero of your field in the coffee line, instead of at the poster session!)</p>
</section>
<section id="rehearse-whenever-you-can" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rehearse-whenever-you-can">Rehearse whenever you can!</h4>
<p>Find 10 volunteers, not necessarily your supervisor only, to test out your 2-minute presentation; while in the lunch line, when waiting for a measurement to finish, or when cleaning the bench.</p>
</section>
<section id="tricks-are-allowed." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tricks-are-allowed.">Tricks are allowed.</h4>
<p>To get people interested in your poster, you can use tricks. Have handouts ready to take home, bring a laptop to show movies, I’ve seen people hand out sweets, and know someone that served beers – everything is allowed when trying to convince people to read your poster!</p>
</section>
<section id="further-reading" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="further-reading">Further reading:</h4>
<p>A really nice paper on how to give a poster presentation is here: “Producing punchy posters” by Bernard S. Brown, in Trends in Cell biology, Vol. 6, 1996. He mainly deals with text, and less with figures, but has been helpful for me for 20 years! <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/0962892496810373?via%3Dihub">link to article</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>datavis</category>
  <category>PosterDesign</category>
  <category>how-to</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Poster_2020/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Poster_2020/color_code.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="102" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Visual aids for patient empowerment</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/MedArxiv/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="datavis-at-the-oncology-unit" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="datavis-at-the-oncology-unit">Datavis at the oncology unit</h4>
<p>You all know I love data visualizations for science communication. But in the past 5 years, I worked in the oncology unit, and started to research how visual aids can be effectively used in cancer care.</p>
<p>When cancer patients begin treatment, they feel overwhelmed, anxious, and intimidated by the hospital setting. This stress can significantly reduce how much information they retain. On average, patients remember only about 20% of the critical treatment details provided by their healthcare team.</p>
<div id="fig-visualaid" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center quarto-float anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-visualaid-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/MedArxiv/plan.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-visualaid-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;1: Example visual aid for communicating treatment path for a patient with multiple myeloma.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="visual-aid-comprehension" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visual-aid-comprehension">Visual aid comprehension</h4>
<p>To bridge this health literacy gap and enhance treatment adherence, we explored the use of visual aids to support doctor-patient communication during cancer treatments. Our study reveals that these visual aids are not only clear and easy to understand, but also significantly improve comprehension of medical information and prove highly beneficial in clinical settings.</p>
<div id="fig-anna" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center quarto-float anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-anna-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/MedArxiv/Anna_PR.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-anna-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;2: Visual aids increasd participants response quality and confidence. Based on questionnaire with 160 participants.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We for example showed that the response quality was increased,from 68% to 84%, when participants were informed about cancer treatment with a visual aid. More importantly, these aids boosted participants’ confidence in their understanding and led to higher ratings of information quality. We also assessed the clarity of the visual aids; the pictograms used to represent key terms were mostly interpretable and considered effective by 300 participants.</p>
<div id="fig-julian" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center quarto-float anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-julian-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/MedArxiv/Julian_PR.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-julian-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;3: Example of visual representations for “hospital” - pictogram and comic were much more guessable than photo. Based on questionnaire of 306 participants.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="patients-use-of-visual-aids" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="patients-use-of-visual-aids">Patients use of visual aids</h4>
<p>A critical part of our research focused on the patient experiences (all approved by ethics board). With the help of visual aids, patients were able to better understand and remember their treatment paths, retaining key information for several weeks. Both patients and physicians found the visual aids to be very helpful, and many patients kept and treasured their aids.</p>
<div id="fig-patients" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center quarto-float anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-patients-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/MedArxiv/Patient_PR.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-patients-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;4: Patient responses to qualitative questions. Based on interviews with 30 patients.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Our work underscores the value of visual aids in clinical settings and motivates us to continue working towards greater equity in patient-centered care and improving doctor-patient communication. Stay tuned for more updates!</p>
<p>Read our paper on <a href="https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2024.06.04.24308420v1">MedArxiv</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>datavis</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/MedArxiv/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/MedArxiv/plan.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="69" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>10 simple rules for Graphical Abstracts</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/24_1_ploscb/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="thank-you-for-providing-me-with-an-exciting-and-informative-read-which-was-truly-enjoyable." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thank-you-for-providing-me-with-an-exciting-and-informative-read-which-was-truly-enjoyable.">“Thank you for providing me with an exciting and informative read which was truly enjoyable.”</h4>
<p>Never have I ever had such great responses from reviewers - it was a joy to attend to the few very good suggestions they had for improving the manuscript! Reviewer 2 and 3 were similarly enthusiastic: “Congratulations for laying out your perspective.” and “Overall, the paper is a beneficial guide for researchers looking to effectively communicate their research through graphical abstracts.” A day to mark in my calendar!</p>
<p>I am happy to finally share with you that the summary of my Graphical Abstract blogs (<a href="../../posts/GraphicalAbstract_1/index.html">here</a>, <a href="../../posts/GraphicalAbstracts_2/index.html">here</a>, <a href="../../posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/GraphicalAbstracts.html">and here</a> is now available as paper for you all to read and cite! Out in <a href="https://dx.plos.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011789">PLOS Computational Biology.</a></p>
<div id="fig-overview" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/24_1_ploscb/Slide6.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: Stages of a graphical abstract - from inception to implementation.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>datavis</category>
  <category>how-to</category>
  <category>Graphical abstracts</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/24_1_ploscb/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/24_1_ploscb/PLOSCB.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="130" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Advent-doodling</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="my-advent-of-doodles" class="level1">
<h1>My Advent of doodles</h1>
<p>I sketch a little something most days, usually in the morning. Hence, I make a lot of drawings of my mug or other breakfast items. In December, I wanted to explore ways for encoding quantities. Starting from 1 all the way to 24 I tried out different marks to show increasingly large numbers. I was wondering which would be clear, or easy to decode, or just pretty. Enjoy my little data-vis advent calendar!</p>
<div id="fig-one" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: 1 is tricky - it needs something around, a frame, to really focus the attention on the one dot, or the one mark etc. When it is enclosed by a rectangle it appears more like position is communicated - not the quantity. 2 items can already form a line, a visual group - it is getting easier to recognize that a quantity is shown. I like the mountains and waves :) And, again, the Cartesian coordinates are confusing and distract from a quantity.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div id="fig-three" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/3.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/4.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: 3 works nicely with dots, lines or rectanges, and still works with waves and mountains. 3 was fun! Oh, and 4 was even more fun - maybe I am also getting the hang ot it. I tried dots, lines, round lines, rectangles, clouds and drops. I feel like the “stairs” going up is not working at all - and also waves and dots in RANDOM (bottom left) order is getting tricky already.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div id="fig-five" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/5.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/6.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;3: Fun ways for 5 - i think it is most clear when items are neatly arranged. The many fun ways, flowers starts etc work probalby a lot better as multiples - when we can compare petal number or flame number etc. Now: 6! Pity I used a blue pen! But I leave it - errors are the beauty of real sketches. Six is not possible at all anymore as waves! And surprisingly tricky as petals - it may be me, but an uneven number is much better to see!</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div id="fig-seven" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/7.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/8.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;4: Impossible to see at first glance “7” in and of these. Too much for visually comprehension? We are now at “Magic number 7”, the limit Miller defined we can perceive pre-attentively. Given that seven was already challenging for me, I started to play with groupings for 8. Two lines, two rows of rectangles etc. The only iterations that I find easy are the tile-array (bottom left) and the system used in pubs etc, of four lines where fifth line goes across.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div id="fig-nine" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/9.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/10.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;5: Same as eight, 9 works best when it forms groups. Really easy are 3x3 goups, or rectangles, lines, or dots. I even once supported grouping by proximity with an enclosure (looks like 3 traffic lights sideways, third row, second from right), I know the Gestalt principles! For 10 mostly same as nine - if grouped it works well (second row right examples), even with tricky shapes (bottom line, little “plants”).</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div id="fig-11-14" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/11.png" id="fig-11" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300" alt="11"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/12.png" id="fig-12" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300" alt="12"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/13.png" id="fig-13" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300" alt="13"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/14.png" id="fig-14" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300" alt="14"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;6: I have given up on being able to visually count - instead I just play around with shapes and groups. Readable imo are only the few that are using the talling system.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div id="fig-15-18" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/15.png" id="fig-15" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300" alt="15"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/16.png" id="fig-16" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300" alt="16"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/17.png" id="fig-17" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300" alt="17"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/18.png" id="fig-18" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300" alt="18"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;7: 15 to 18…. Getting messier! If you want clarity, tallying is the only hope, but for attraction the grouped flowers are starting to become interesting - and interesting is not bad, it captures attention and let’s readers linger a little longer.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div id="fig-19-24" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/19.png" id="fig-19" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300" alt="19"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/20.png" id="fig-20" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300" alt="20"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/21.png" id="fig-21" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300" alt="21"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/22.png" id="fig-22" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300" alt="22"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/23.png" id="fig-23" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300" alt="23"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/24.png" id="fig-24" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300" alt="24"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;8: Oh well, at this point it does not matter anymore, but there are now so many items it becomes joyful to look at. Symmetries can be formed and broken, which is interesting! And flower bed are blooming :=)</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This was fun! I guess there really is no point going onwards to New Years. The more items we got, the more important becomes their layouting and organisation. Happy new year and see you for next years advent challenge!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>datavis</category>
  <category>sketches</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/post_Advent/StrikingImage.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="110" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Truthful images</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_JCS/TruthInImages.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="do-images-tell-the-truth" class="level1">
<h1>Do images tell the truth?</h1>
<p>Objectivity and truth matter in scientific images, especially as we use them to communicate insights about life and the universe. Today, AI is igniting debates in microscopy imaging. Does AI accurately emnhances reality? Are hallucinations introduced? And what defines a truly “raw” image in the era of advanced microscopes? For the Christmas edition of the <a href="https://journals.biologists.com/jcs/article/136/24/jcs261837/337758/A-community-driven-approach-to-enhancing-the?guestAccessKey=eb13a893-aad0-4291-a2f6-3748eb1941b4">Journal of Cell Sciences</a>, I wrote about our community efforts towards improving images in publication and put our work into a historical perspective.</p>
<div id="fig-ai" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_JCS/split_tribolium2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: Content-aware image restoration - one of the first applications of AI in confocal microscopy images. From <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41592-018-0216-7"> Weigert et al 2018</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="enlightenment-drawings" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="enlightenment-drawings">Enlightenment &amp; drawings</h2>
<p>Debates about truth in images did not arise with AI. While the imaging methods are new, the discussions about image objectivity has long historical roots. In the Enlightenment era, similar discussions happened around drawings, and duelists were the observing scientists, their scientific illustrators and copperplate engravers. Even then, achieving objectivity was tough and “fixing the empirically variable, excluding the accidental, and eliminating the impure,” as Goethe noted, was daunting in images.</p>
</section>
<section id="photography" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="photography">Photography</h2>
<p>Photography was a game-changer in the 18 hundreds, as AI is today. Arthur Worthington’s captures this well. Worthington drew the shape of falling drops in their nearly otherworldly symmetry. Shocked by his first photos, revealing the irregular nature of the splashes, he wrote “the mind of the observer is filled with an ideal splash, whose perfection may never be realized.” Highly recommend his book “Romance of Science Series - The Splash of a Drop” - free <a href="http://archive.org/details/splashofdrop00wortuoft">on the Internet Archive</a>.</p>
<div id="fig-overview" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_JCS/Slide2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: Worthingtons splashes looked strikingly different in drawings and first photographs.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="image-adjustments-then-and-now" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="image-adjustments-then-and-now">Image adjustments, then and now</h2>
<p>Early photography needed a lot of “effort and artifice” (Daston, Objectivity). Early pics were often coarse and had to be tweeked to show anything at all. What was acceptable and what was misleading? An <a href="https://archive.org/details/b2192532x">early textbook for microscopy images</a> from 1890 gives us a clue: splicing images was commonly practiced for efficiency, while altering background colors raised concerns about potential manipulation. Its author Neuhauss also writes that “all measures that uniformly impact the entire image are unequivocally permissible,” a notion almost unchanged in contemporary guides for the now digital images (Cromey, 2013).</p>
<div id="fig-neuhauss" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_JCS/Neuhauss_Photomicrograph.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;3: A photo-micrograph captured by Neuhauss, likely adhering to the good practice of image processing postulated in his book.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="community-efforts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="community-efforts">Community efforts</h2>
<p>The gap between what scientists see and what tech shows will remain. Bridging it and finding consensus what images tell the truth will always need collective efforts and debates in the scientific community.</p>
<p>Read the full article and many more about community<a href="https://journals.biologists.com/jcs/article/136/24/jcs261837/337758/A-community-driven-approach-to-enhancing-the?guestAccessKey=eb13a893-aad0-4291-a2f6-3748eb1941b4"> here.</a></p>
<section id="more-reading" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="more-reading">More reading</h3>
My blog series about image handling:
<ul>
<li>
How to… image formatting (August 1) <a href="../../posts/Image_how_mag/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
How to… image scale information (August 3) <a href="../../posts/Image_how_scale/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
How to… image annotation (August 8) <a href="../../posts/Image_how_annot/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
How to… image colors (August 10) <a href="../../posts/Image_how_color/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
How to… image availability (August 15) <a href="../../posts/Image_how_avail/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
Cheat sheets for image publishing (August 21) <a href="../../posts/Image_cheatsheets/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
A short history of science images (August 27) <a href="../../posts/Image_history/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
How to… image analysis (Sept 20) <a href="../../posts/Image_how_analysis/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
How to… avoid misleading with images (Sept 22) <a href="../../posts/Image_misleading/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Our community effort for image publication, out in Nature Methods:</p>
<div id="fig-checklists" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_JCS/Slide1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;4: Checklists for image and image analyses publication.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>
</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>history</category>
  <category>images</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_JCS/TruthInImages.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_JCS/Slide2.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="90" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Science&amp;Art at ASCB CellBio23</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/ASCB/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="saturday-is-art-day-at-ascb" class="level1">
<h1>Saturday is Art-Day at ASCB!</h1>
<p>Last week I was invited to the <a href="https://www.ascb.org/cellbio2023/program/subgroups/">ASCB Subgroup “Science and Art: Bridging Two Creative Universes“ </a>. Artists shows subjective views of the world, while biologists measure life, which seem like opposites. Where they converge is in their shared goal to communicate their ideas and insights. And nowhere are they as close as in the communication with data visualizations.</p>
<section id="what-i-spoke-about" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-i-spoke-about">What I spoke about</h2>
<p>I am neither a cell biologist (anymore), nor an artist. But my work is to make data understandable through visualization. Data visualization is about finding truthful, insightful, and pleasing representations for messy, uncertain, and complicated biological data. And to create effective visualizations, we use techniques from the arts. I am fully behind the notion of the organisers, that there is an “impact of artistic practices on scientific research and communication“. In my talk I show how concepts from art make data visualizations work.</p>
<div id="fig-overview" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/ASCB/Slide1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: Art concepts we use in data visualization</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="representation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="representation">Representation</h2>
<p>Art expresses itself in many representations, from sculpture to video, and these evolve over time. In data visualizations we also rely on a pool of representations we can choose from, and these are the chart types. Each serves a different purpose, some are intuitive, and others require prior training.</p>
<div id="fig-rep" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/ASCB/Slide2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: Pick a suitable representation for your data. For numerical data numerous charts exists and new forms keep being invented.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="abstraction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstraction">Abstraction</h2>
<p>Abstraction is used constantly in science. We take a picture of cute animals, make continuous observations of molecular interactions, or take snapshots of genomes – each is a simplification into 1s and 0s, which then can be averaged, correlated, and tested.</p>
<div id="fig-abtr" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/ASCB/Slide3.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;3: All data are just 1s and 0s.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="pattern-recognition" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pattern-recognition">Pattern recognition</h2>
<p>When we turn 1s and 0s into visualizations for inspection, we use of the preattentive cues to find outliers, patterns or to draw attention.</p>
<div id="fig-ptterns" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/ASCB/Slide4.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;4: Our eyes see visual cues such as line width, color, decorations, and absences.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="rules" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rules">Rules</h2>
<p>Data visualization relies on human visual perception. From magicians, we that our visual senses can be tricked. In science we want to avoid this to not mislead our audiences. Therefore, we established rules for scientists how to faithfully present data.</p>
<div id="fig-rules" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/ASCB/Slide5.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/ASCB/Slide6.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/ASCB/Slide7.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;5: Resources: Tracey’s paper about <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.1002128"> misleading bar charts</a>, our paper about <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">unclear image figures</a>, our workflow, with cheatsheets!, for <a href="https://f1000research.com/articles/9-1373/v2">image processing</a>, and our checklists for publishing <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41592-023-01987-9"> image data</a>.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="break-rules" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="break-rules">Break rules</h2>
<p>At times, we see that rules get broken. Currently, against best practice, 3D-effects are making a comeback in charts. Usually, these charts do not necessarily want to present data the best way, but merely grab the attention of the visually overstimulated audience.</p>
<div id="fig-breakrules" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/ASCB/Slide8.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;6: Trained data visualizers consider 3D effects misleading - a new generation seems to disagree and fancy some cool effects here and there!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="emotional-response" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="emotional-response">Emotional response</h2>
<p>The purpose of attention grabbing is to elicit an emotional response. Emotional responses get people engaged and known to enhance comprehension and memory. Any emotional response works for this, so in art and data visualization we can use humor, horror and of course beauty. For our patient communication project used a calming and somewhat pretty visualization to help cancer patients understand their treatment course.</p>
<div id="fig-emotion" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/ASCB/Slide9.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;7: Emotions help us understand and remember.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="fashion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fashion">Fashion</h2>
<p>Just as in art, also in data visualization we are not impartial to trends. Just check out the below iterations of a figure - can you guess which was fashionable when? Check out <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.10.24.563757v3">Isaac and James paper</a> to find out which we considered pretty in 2023 - and how they show us that cells can survive happily with JUST TWO LIPIDS!</p>
<div id="fig-fashion" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/ASCB/Paper_Figure5_231107_variations2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;8: Each generation has their favorite color scheme for data.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="some-more-literature" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="some-more-literature">Some more literature</h2>
<p>Get all the reading material, including the first book on data visualization for life science from 1885!</p>
<div id="fig-link" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/ASCB/Slide10.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;9: Scan link for lots of papers. Or not.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="my-wonderful-colleagues" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="my-wonderful-colleagues">My wonderful colleagues</h2>
<p>Please also check out the great work by all the other speakers: <a href="https://ccsb.scripps.edu/goodsell/">Dave Goodsell</a> does not need any introduction, his work is shared widely and who has not seen the colorful structures of cells! <a href="https://humantechnopole.it/en/people/gaia-pigino/">Gaia Pigino</a> explored ways to use art to even make her own science more fun for herself, while Mary O’Reilly shared fun ways to increase creativity in our illustrations and Christopher Prinz told his personal story of heightening the game of his lab with art. Thao Do and Mol Mir try to bring art to the scientists in their respective institutes, while Leonora Martínez-Nuñez uses art to publicize science to a public. Representation with sculptures was definingly a theme, maybe we need some haptic, real-world objects after a decade of big data. We learned about ceramics from Duygu Ozpolat, glass art from Alex Ritter, and metal welding from Bryan Welm. And finally, <a href="https://new.mica.edu/undergraduate-majors-minors/game-design-major/melanie-stegman/">Melanie Stegman</a> introduced a relatively new format, video games, as another flower in the bouquet of possibilities to make science fun and accessible to wide audiences. In the evening we got a chance to visit the SEAS Disease Biophysics Group headed by Kit Parker. They are trying to advance bioengineering in many directions but also incorporate creative techniques of the arts into their research and artists into their labs - for a fruitful exchange if ideas and apporaches. And were treated to “drumroll” WALKING TACOs! I did eat out of a bag for the first time in my life.</p>
<div id="fig-taco" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/ASCB/WalkingTaco_helena.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="150"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;10: Walking taco, skeptical look is before diggin’ in!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A big thank you to the organizers, <a href="https://beatascienceart.com/about/">Beata Mierzwa</a>, Francesca Bartolini and Carsten Janke!!</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>datavis</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/ASCB/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/ASCB/Slide1.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="55" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to… avoid Misleading images</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_misleading/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I care about science and images that is widely accessible. At present, that is not always the case. Image figures are confusing and unclear. I have <a href="../../posts/Image_numbers/index.html">written</a> and <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161"> published</a> about communicating understandable image data, and last week <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41592-023-01987-9">our community-developed guidelines for publishing understandable images</a> got published.</p>
<p>For scientists it is worth investing time in producing clear papers: incomprehensible data is demonstrably less read, less often cited, and unlikely to be included in the scientific canon. Don’t believe me? <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26361556/">Letchford et al</a> have data!</p>
<div id="fig-letch" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_misleading/Letchford.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: From Letchford et al.&nbsp;2015, doi: 10.1098/rsos.150266.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="accidentally-misleading-images" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="accidentally-misleading-images">Accidentally misleading images</h2>
<p>Published images at times are not just unclear but misleading. This may be because image data was incorrectly processed. I <a href="../../posts/Image_how_mag/index.html">previously wrote about one example published by Miura and Norrelykke</a>, which illustrated that the sequence of contrast adjustment and image cropping matter. I regularly witness the education gap in image handling in my DataViz courses. Graduate students ask: Is it ok to turn images? Can I crop away a neighboring cell? Am I allowed to show green fluorescent protein in red? When images are processed without in-depth knowledge of the software, accidentally misleading images may be the result.</p>
<div id="fig-kota" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_misleading/Kota.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: Sequence matters when adjusting brightness contrast. Adapted from <a href="https://doi.org/10.15252/embj.2020105889">Miura &amp; Norrelykke</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div id="fig-chris" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_misleading/Turning_Images.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;3: How turning/transforming images can falsify intensity distributions in image data, example from Christopher Schmied.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="actually-misleading-images" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="actually-misleading-images">Actually misleading images</h2>
<p>Less common than accidentally misleading images, are instances of intentional image manipulation. These are cases when authors fabricate or forge data to mislead audiences. Elisabeth Bik has brought attention to this problem and also quantified instances of image manipulations in publications.</p>
<div id="fig-fraud" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_misleading/BikBlog.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;4: Example of “composed” image, that contains cloned/spliced image parts, from <a href="https://twitter.com/MicrobiomDigest">Elisabeth Bik</a>.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="guidelines-to-avoid-misleading-images" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="guidelines-to-avoid-misleading-images">Guidelines to avoid misleading images</h2>
<p>Already before Biks quantification and activism, early community initiatives of scientists and editors clarified what counts as image manipulation and which image processing is acceptable for publication. The CSE guidelines are long and update annually! Here is the relevant section on digital image:</p>
<div id="fig-cse" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_misleading/CSE2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;5: CSE 3.4.1 Guidelines for Handling Image Data</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="read-more" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="read-more">Read more</h2>
<p>Bik, E.M., Casadevall, A., Fang, F.C., 2016.<a href="https://doi.org/10.1128/mBio.00809-16">The Prevalence of Inappropriate Image Duplication in Biomedical Research Publications.</a> mBio 7.</p>
<div id="fig-bik2" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_misleading/BikPaper.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;6: Example in publication.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="accurate-and-reproducible-image-quality" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="accurate-and-reproducible-image-quality">Accurate and reproducible image quality</h4>
<ul>
<li>
Brown, C.M., 2007. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1242/jcs.03433">Fluorescence microscopy–avoiding the pitfalls. J Cell Sci 120, 1703–1705.</a>
</li>
<li>
Faklaris, O., Bancel-Vallée, L., Dauphin, A., Monterroso, B., Frère, P., Geny, D., Manoliu, T., de Rossi, S., Cordelières, F.P., Schapman, D., Nitschke, R., Cau, J., Guilbert, T., 2022. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1083/jcb.202107093
">Quality assessment in light microscopy for routine use through simple tools and robust metrics. Journal of Cell Biology 221.</a>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="recommendations-to-avoid-misleading-images" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recommendations-to-avoid-misleading-images">Recommendations to avoid misleading images</h4>
<ul>
<li>
Bik, E.M., Fang, F.C., Kullas, A.L., Davis, R.J., Casadevall, A., 2018. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1128/MCB.00309-18">Analysis and Correction of Inappropriate Image Duplication: the Molecular and Cellular Biology Experience.</a>
</li>
<li>
Cromey, D.W., 2013. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-62703-056-4_1">Digital images are data: and should be treated as such.</a>
</li>
<li>
CSE’s White Paper on <a href="http://www.councilscienceeditors.org/wp-content/uploads/entire_whitepaper.pdf">Promoting Integrity in Scientific Journal Publications</a>
</li>
<li>
North, A.J., 2006. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1083/jcb.200507103">Seeing is believing? A beginners’ guide to practical pitfalls in image acquisition.</a>
</li>
<li>
Rossner, M., Yamada, K.M., 2004. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1083/jcb.200406019">What’s in a picture? The temptation of image manipulation.</a>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="detection-of-manipulated-image-data" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="detection-of-manipulated-image-data">Detection of manipulated image data</h4>
<ul>
<li>
Bucci, E.M., 2018. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41419-018-0430-3">Automatic detection of image manipulations in the biomedical literature.</a>
</li>
<li>
Koppers, L., Wormer, H., Ickstadt, K., 2017. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11948-016-9841-7">Towards a Systematic Screening Tool for Quality Assurance and Semiautomatic Fraud Detection for Images in the Life Sciences.</a>
</li>
<li>
Van Noorden, R., 2022. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-021-03807-6">Journals adopt AI to spot duplicated images in manuscripts.</a>
</li>
<li>
Van Noorden, R., 2020. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-020-01410-9">Publishers launch joint effort to tackle altered images in research papers.</a>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="appropriate-image-handling-and-analysis" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="appropriate-image-handling-and-analysis">Appropriate image handling and analysis</h4>
<ul>
<li>
Aaron, J., Chew, T.-L., 2021. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1242/jcs.254151">A guide to accurate reporting in digital image processing - can anyone reproduce your quantitative analysis?</a>
</li>
<li>
Hammer, M., Huisman, M., Rigano, A., Boehm, U., Chambers, J.J., Gaudreault, N., North, A.J., Pimentel, J.A., Sudar, D., Bajcsy, P., Brown, C.M., Corbett, A.D., Faklaris, O., Lacoste, J., Laude, A., Nelson, G., Nitschke, R., Farzam, F., Smith, C.S., Grunwald, D., Strambio-De-Castillia, C., 2021. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-021-01327-9">Towards community-driven metadata standards for light microscopy: tiered specifications extending the OME model.</a>
</li>
<li>
Martin, C., Blatt, M., 2013. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1105/tpc.113.250980">Manipulation and misconduct in the handling of image data.</a>
</li>
<li>
Miura, K., Norrelykke, S.F., 2021. <a href="https://doi.org/10.15252/embj.2020105889">Reproducible image handling and analysis.</a>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="guidelines-for-writing-materials-and-methods-sections-for-images" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="guidelines-for-writing-materials-and-methods-sections-for-images">Guidelines for writing materials and methods sections for images</h4>
<ul>
<li>
Marques G, P.T., Sanders MA, 2020. <a href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.55133">Imaging methods are vastly underreported in biomedical research</a>.
</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>images</category>
  <category>how-to</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_misleading/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_misleading/Turning_Images.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="138" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to… image analysis</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Schmied</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_analysis/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>A guest post by Christopher Schmied, find him <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/chrischmied/">on linkedin</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/ChriSchmied">social media</a>.</p>
<section id="hidden-image-analysis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hidden-image-analysis">Hidden image analysis</h2>
<p>As a Research Data Scientist I engage in many different collaborative scientific projects, particularly focusing on the analysis of microscopy image data (Fig. 1). Turning to the scientific literature, I noticed that image analysis methods were often absent or hidden by only briefly mentioning the used image analysis software. This made reproduction often very difficult.</p>
In publications image analysis is only one of many different methods scientists utilize to produce quantitative results. This scientific skill is increasingly taught in many courses at academic institutions. Also many online resources in different formats exist that help scientists to perform image analysis correctly:
<ul>
<li>
Written tutorials: <a href="https://bioimagebook.github.io/">BioImageBook</a>
</li>
<li>
Videos: <a href="https://youtu.be/ZBsjrcYiw-c?si=94OpKKrXc49br3bD">find on e.g., youtube</a>
</li>
<li>
Publications: <a href="https://f1000research.com/articles/9-1373">Start with this &amp; links therein</a>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Furthermore, there is also a growing community of scientists specialized in image analysis. You can get directly in touch with this community via <a href=" https://forum.image.sc/">image.sc</a>. In this forum you can find many solutions and helpful materials, for instance in the following post you will find <a href="https://forum.image.sc/t/bioimage-analysis-recommended-reading-and-viewing/28051
">a vast collection of training materials for image analysis</a>. However, clear instructions or guidelines how image analysis should be documented in research papers were missing. This is another reason that is making it hard for authors to effectively publish good image analysis methods.</p>
<div id="fig-IA" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_analysis/Chris_new.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: Image Analysis: (A) With image analysis workflows quantitative data is extracted from images. (B) Images are data here intensity information is displayed in different ways. (C) Image segmentation allows to extract information such as objects numbers, object sizes, shapes etc.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="bringing-image-analysis-into-the-light" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bringing-image-analysis-into-the-light">Bringing image analysis into the light</h2>
Helena Jambor then started a fantastic effort within Quarep-LiMi to improve publications of microscopy images. She brought me in as a Co-chair and together with many different scientists and experts in image analysis and microscopy we were able to distill core aspects of good image analysis methods in publications. We focused on giving practical and easy to execute advice in three different categories of image analysis methods that we commonly see used in research papers (Fig. Publication of image analysis):
<ul>
<li>
Established workflows
</li><li>
New workflows
</li><li>
Machine learning workflows
</li></ul>
<p>We hope that these checklist will enhance the work of scientists and make their life easier by giving clear and actionable instructions for the publication of images and image analysis.</p>
<section id="read-the-nature-methods-paper-here" class="level6">
<h6 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="read-the-nature-methods-paper-here">Read the Nature Methods paper <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41592-023-01987-9">here</a></h6>
</section>
<section id="find-the-checklist-to-download-as-printable-files-here." class="level6">
<h6 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="find-the-checklist-to-download-as-printable-files-here.">Find the checklist to download as printable files <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7642559">here</a>.</h6>
</section>
<section id="a-companion-jupyter-book-is-available-here." class="level6">
<h6 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-companion-jupyter-book-is-available-here.">A companion Jupyter Book is available <a href="https://quarep-limi.github.io/WG12_checklists_for_image_publishing/intro.html">here</a>.</h6>
<div id="fig-chris" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_analysis/Fig 7.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: Publication of image analysis: Image data is transformed into results using image analysis workflows. In the literature we see that authors use established analysis workflows, new workflows and machine learning workflows. In our checklists we give essential advice on how to publish these methods.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>images</category>
  <category>how-to</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_analysis/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_analysis/intesities.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="102" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Checklists for image publication</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_NM_story/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Our guidelines for image and image analyses publishing just got published for you all <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41592-023-01987-9"> in Nature Methods</a>. This was a long journey, here is how it came about:</p>
<section id="some-images-oh-my" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="some-images-oh-my">Some images, oh my!</h2>
<p>In 2016/2017 I was a fellow at the <a href="https://www.wiko-berlin.de/">Institute for Advanced Studies</a> and prepping a data visualisation curriculum, which included image figures. Screening for teaching examples I found that many, many authors were still happily publishing red/green color combinations in both charts and also in microscopy images, thus making their science visually inaccessible to colour-blind readers <a href="https://thenode.biologists.com/color-blind-audiences/photo/">(see my post at TheNode)</a>.</p>
<div id="fig-red-green" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_NM_story/Colors2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: Problems of showing image data in color.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="we-collected-numbers-oh-dear" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="we-collected-numbers-oh-dear">We collected numbers, OH DEAR!</h2>
<p>At the 2018 <a href="https://meetings.embo.org/event/18-lsm">Light Sheet conference</a> microscopy fans gathered to discuss awesome images. Except me, I was still stunned by the subpar images I had seen in papers. I ended up chatting with Rita Strack, editor at Nature Methods about journal strategies to ensure image figures are legible (none back then!) and my idea for a survey. The idea evolved into a project when I teamed up with Tracey Weissgerber in the eLIFE ambassador programme. Tracey had experience with meta-research (i.e.&nbsp;screening literature) and with out group we analyzed published images with a standardized protocol. Now we had numbers for what previously was just an impression: lots of pictures didn’t have sizes marks, giving readers a little guessing game time. The colors? Turns out, many were like secret codes that only the authors could understand. Plus, the explanations often barely enlightened - check ourpaper <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">in PLOS BIO</a></p>
<div id="fig-plos" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_NM_story/Summary.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: Summary of the PLOS BIO numbers we collected.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="zoom-zoom-zoom-science-in-a-global-network" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="zoom-zoom-zoom-science-in-a-global-network">Zoom, Zoom, Zoom: science in a global network</h2>
<p>Our PLOS BIO paper got me onto the (virtual, remember COVID!) stage of the 2020 meeting of the German Bioimaging society. The Q&amp;A was a lively discussion of many impossible ways to improve image communication and one clear idea: let’s form a <a href="https://quarep.org/">QUAREP</a> working group for this! Starting with just four members, we hashed, clashed, and conjured what eventually became the checklists for image publishing. Quickly our <a href="https://quarep.org/working-groups/wg-12-image-visualization-and-analysis/">Working Group 12</a> grew and became very interdisciplinary: we have members from research institutes, medical clinics, and even NASA; from all continents and time-zones; from applied research, companies and theory. Safe to say, we also at times failed to find a consensus and tip toed around some topics until we dropped them. Our opinions also differed on how strict we wanted to be with guidelines but also there found a workable compromise between our ideals and reality. In the end, all scientists globally, also those with little access to advanced microscopy facilities, should be empowered to reach the minimal goals, while at the same time we also wanted to push some higher image and image analysis standards. This lead to the the three levels, mandatory, recommended and ideal.</p>
<div id="fig-evolution" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_NM_story/checklistEvolution.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;3: Evolution of the checklists. From white-silver-gold to Recommended and Ideal. Only icons were always there, everything else changed.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="a-paper-emerges" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-paper-emerges">A paper emerges</h2>
<p>Fuelled by caffeine and italian carbs at the Human Technopole in Milan, a writing-weekend produced the first draft that was improved in feedback rounds with many of our QUAREP-LiMi friends and colleages. The extended vetting was helpful, with just one round of small revisions our manuscript was accepted by our first choice journal, Nature Methods. Coincidentally, it was handled by Rita Strack, who I believe does not even remember our brief coffee line conversation about this project many years agon! And now we give the checklists to all of you scientists – These are not lists, but the audacious result of chasing pixel perfection in scientific zoom calls. For me personally it was a rewarding experience to collaborate with so many people, and from now I will keep meeting co-authors at many meetings to come!</p>
<div id="fig-meeting" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_NM_story/HTBesuch2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_NM_story/IMG_2346.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;4: HT Milan where Helena &amp; Christopher wrote the first draft in Sept 2022 and for relaxation played with Chloe (dog). Below celebrating with 10% of the author team at PoLBIAS23, Sept 2023.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>images</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_NM_story/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_NM_story/Checklist_Image_2023-05-10.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="208" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>(A very short) History of Bio-Images</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_history/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="a-very-short-history-of-bio-images" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-very-short-history-of-bio-images">(A very short) History of Bio-Images</h2>
<p>Images communicate scientific observations long before photography and light microscopy were invented. The first evidences of images were drawings in medical and pharmaceutical text books from antiquity. While these drawings to us today seem almost like art, they very much served a scientific purpose. See the example below, in which objects are aligned, oriented, and size-standardized to allow readers to compare various poisonous scorpions.</p>
<div id="fig-antique" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_history/Stückelberger.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: Poisonous scorpions, medical textbook ~200 AD, transcript ~500 AD. From: Alfred Stückelberger, Bild und Wort</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>For most of their time scientific drawings and copper plates intentionally showed “average” observations, not individual specimen. The drawings were in fact an overlay, idealized version of single animals and plants. They also came with key information: Maria Sibylla Merian and others who documented nature explained the <a href="../../posts/Image_how_scale/index.html">size of specimen</a> in their drawings and often included known insects that could double as scale information.</p>
</section>
<section id="photography" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="photography">Photography</h2>
<p>With the advent of photography, publications started to include photos and microscopic images of specimen. A pioneer of photographic images in biology and medicine was the physiologist Marey. Étienne-Jules Marey, a French physiologist, developed many medical apparatuses, and notably the first “chronophotographic gun” in 1882 which allowed him to capture twelve frames per second on the same picture to document the rapid movements of animal and human locomotion. Notably, Marey also authored the first text book of data visualizing for physiology, introducing many scientists to charts and how to use photo images as evidence in biomedicine. The book, La Méthode graphique dans les sciences expérimentales can be viewed online in French (Text on line) and was <a href="https://medium.com/nightingale/information-graphic-visionaries-6dda1a0b8056">recently translated by George Hattab and RJ Andrews</a>.</p>
<div id="fig-marey" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_history/Etienne_Jules_Marey_.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: Marey invented a method to study locomotion with photography</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>At the turn of the last century, the first photographs appeared in scientific journals and slowly photos were used to document biological observations made through the microscope, e.g.&nbsp;Newth’s microscopic image of lamprey’s larvae. At the same time, Friedrich Kopsch in Berlin captured serial time-lapse images to document gastrulation in axolotl and frog eggs.</p>
<div id="fig-newth" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_history/Newth.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;3: Photo by Newth in Nature, July, 1930 documents feeding of an Amphioxus larva</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Image in scientific publications however were not always well received – in a letter to the editor, Benjamin Moore complained in 1910 that:</p>
<div id="fig-moore" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_history/BMoore_1910.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;4: Letter to the Editor, Nature</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The invention of fluorescent markers and techniques to couple these to antibodies by Albert Coons made light microscopy a mainstream technique widely accepted and images became accepted as data also outside its core application fields, embryology and morphology. With the invention of photography, and in particular digital photo-micrography, a steady increase in images figures is noticeable in scientific articles. Today <a href="../../posts/Image_numbers/index.html">20% of the articles indexed in PubMed</a> contain image figures and in the minutes you spend reading this article, 5 new publications with images will appear.</p>
<div id="fig-fluo" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_history/Horio_Hotani_1986_Video.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;5: One of the first videos with a fluorescent microscope, published by Horio and Hotani 1986</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="more-literature-on-scientific-images" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="more-literature-on-scientific-images">More literature on scientific images</h4>
<ul>
<li>
A seminal book that describes how images became data in science: Daston L, &amp; Peter Galison, P. . Objectivity. New York: Zone Books; 2007
</li>
<li>
A book in German that outlines the history of science images: Stückelberger A. Bild und Wort: Das illustrierte Fachbuch in der antiken Naturwissenschaft, Medizin und Technik: P. von Zabern; 1994
</li>
<li>
A book about early observations and images in embryology.Wellmann J. Model and movement: studying cell movement in early morphogenesis, 1900 to the present. Hist Philos Life Sci. 2018;40(3):59.
</li>
<li>
NEWTH, H. The Feeding of Ammocœtes. Nature 126, 94–95 (1930) <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/126094b0">Article</a>
</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>images</category>
  <category>history</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_history/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_history/Marey.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cheat sheet Image preparation</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_cheatsheets/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="cheat-sheets-for-image-publishing" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cheat-sheets-for-image-publishing">Cheat sheets for Image publishing</h2>
<p>Images, initially drawings now photos, are <a href="../../posts/Image_history/index.html">widely used in biology and medicine</a> but when published <a href="../../posts/Image_numbers/index.html">not always understandable</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="image-workflow-for-novice-users" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="image-workflow-for-novice-users">Image Workflow for Novice Users</h2>
<p>When preparing images for publication, the sequence and proper use of software matters to truthfully report observations. During the first lock down, Christopher Schmied and I therefore created cheat sheets that explain a most basic workflow to get everyone from microscope data to figure in a few simple steps.</p>
</section>
<section id="cheat-sheets" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cheat-sheets">Cheat Sheets</h2>
<p>The workflow is summarized in two printable cheat sheets. One cheat sheet explains the steps towards a publishable image, the second cheat sheet how to implement the steps with ImageJ/FIJI image processing software.</p>
<div id="fig-helena" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_cheatsheets/SchmiedJambor_Figure4.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Cheat sheet that explains all steps and commands in FIJI to process and image for publication"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: Preparing an image for publication: a quick design reference. From: <a href="https://f1000research.com/articles/9-1373">Schmied and Jambor. Effective image visualization for publications - a workflow using open access tools and concepts</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div id="fig-chris" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_cheatsheets/SchmiedJambor_Figure3.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Cheat sheet that explains all steps and commands in FIJI to process and image for publication"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: Processing image: a quick guide how to do this in FIJI. From: <a href="https://f1000research.com/articles/9-1373">Schmied and Jambor. Effective image visualization for publications - a workflow using open access tools and concepts </a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="download" class="level5">
<h5 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="download">Download</h5>
<p>Get the cheat sheets as <a href="https://osf.io/cjp8w/">printable PDF</a>. Note, we used an open license, that means you can get the adaptable files and e.g., make translations, alterations, or add your own notes.</p>
<p>A German version was already made by <a href="https://joram.schwartzmann.de/cheat-sheet-wissenschaftliche-abbildungen.html">Joram Schwartzmann</a>, checkt it out!</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="further-resources" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="further-resources">Further resources</h2>
<p>Beyond our starter cheat sheets more great resources help you along the way: The “Biologist’s guide to planning and performing quantitative bioimaging experiments” describes the entire arc from sample to microscope via image analysis towards data interpretation and publication. The resource lists many key points and aggregates links to more detailed descriptions, making it easy for biologists to navigate their first microscopy experiments.</p>
<div id="fig-senft" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_cheatsheets/Senft.PNG" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;3: A biologist’s guide to planning and performing quantitative bioimaging experiments <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002167">Senft RA, Diaz-Rohrer B, Colarusso P, Swift L, Jamali N, Jambor H, et al.&nbsp;(2023) PLoS Biol</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="more-about" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="more-about">More about</h2>
<section id="microscopy-image-acquisition" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="microscopy-image-acquisition">Microscopy image acquisition</h4>
<ul>
<li>
Seeing is believing? A beginners’ guide to practical pitfalls in image acquisition. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1083/jcb.200507103">North, A.J., 2006. J Cell Biol</a>
</li>
<li>
Fluorescence microscopy–avoiding the pitfalls. J<a href="https://doi.org/10.1242/jcs.03433">Brown, C.M., 2007. Cell Sci 120, 1703–1705. </a>
</li>
<li>
Rigor and Reproducibility in Confocal Fluorescence Microscopy. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/cyto.a.23924">Jonkman, J., 2020. Cytometry A</a>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="fluorophores-and-filters" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fluorophores-and-filters">Fluorophores and Filters</h4>
<ul>
<li>
Optimizing live-cell fluorescence imaging conditions to minimize phototoxicity. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1242/jcs.242834">Kiepas, A., Voorand, E., Mubaid, F., Siegel, P.M., Brown, C.M., 2020. J Cell Sci. </a>
</li>
<li>
Assessing phototoxicity in live fluorescence imaging.<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.4344">Laissue, P.P., Alghamdi, R.A., Tomancak, P., Reynaud, E.G., Shroff, H., 2017. Nat Methods</a>
</li>
<li>
Recommendations for a standardized nomenclature for probe tags used in cytometry and microscopy imaging<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/cyto.a.24224">Blenman, K.R.M., Spidlen, J., Parks, D.R., Moore, W., Treister, A., Leif, R., Bray, C., Goldberg, M., ISAC Data Standards Task Force, Brinkman, R., 2021. ISAC Probe Tag Dictionary: Standardized Nomenclature for Detection and Visualization Labels Used in Cytometry and Microscopy Imaging. Cytometry A</a>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="sample-preparation" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sample-preparation">Sample preparation</h4>
<ul>
<li>
Seeing is believing? A beginners’ guide to practical pitfalls in image acquisition. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1083/jcb.200507103">North, A.J., 2006. J Cell Biol</a>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="method-reporting" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="method-reporting">Method reporting</h4>
<ul>
<li>
Towards community-driven metadata standards for light microscopy: tiered specifications extending the OME model.<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-021-01327-9">Hammer, M., Huisman, M., Rigano, A., Boehm, U., Chambers, J.J., Gaudreault, N., North, A.J., Pimentel, J.A., Sudar, D., Bajcsy, P., Brown, C.M., Corbett, A.D., Faklaris, O., Lacoste, J., Laude, A., Nelson, G., Nitschke, R., Farzam, F., Smith, C.S., Grunwald, D., Strambio-De-Castillia, C., 2021. Nat Methods</a>
</li>
<li>
A guide to accurate reporting in digital image acquisition - can anyone replicate your microscopy data?<a href="https://doi.org/10.1242/jcs.254144">Heddleston, J.M., Aaron, J.S., Khuon, S., Chew, T.-L., 2021. J Cell Sci</a>
</li>
<li>
Best practices and tools for reporting reproducible fluorescence microscopy methods. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-021-01156-w">Montero Llopis, P., Senft, R.A., Ross-Elliott, T.J., Stephansky, R., Keeley, D.P., Koshar, P., Marqués, G., Gao, Y.-S., Carlson, B.R., Pengo, T., Sanders, M.A., Cameron, L.A., Itano, M.S., 2021. Nat Methods</a>
</li>
<li>
Imaging methods are vastly underreported in biomedical research. <a href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.55133">Marques G, P.T., Sanders MA, 2020. Elife</a>
</li>
<li>
Micro-Meta App: an interactive tool for collecting microscopy metadata based on community specifications.<a href="">Rigano, A. et al.&nbsp;Nat. Methods</a>
</li>
<li>
MethodsJ2: a software tool to capture metadata and generate comprehensive microscopy methods text. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-021-01290-5">Ryan, J., Pengo, T., Rigano, A., Llopis, P.M., Itano, M.S., Cameron, L.A., Marqués, G., Strambio-De-Castillia, C., Sanders, M.A., Brown, C.M., 2021. Nat Methods</a>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="image-analysis-processing-software" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="image-analysis-processing-software">Image analysis &amp; processing software</h4>
<ul>
<li>
Fiji: an open-source platform for biological-image analysis.<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nmeth.2019">Schindelin J, Arganda-Carreras I, Frise E, Kaynig V, Longair M, Pietzsch T, et al.&nbsp;Nature methods</a>
</li>
<li>
A Hitchhiker’s guide through the bio-image analysis software universe.<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/1873-3468.14451">Haase, R., Fazeli, E., Legland, D., Doube, M., Culley, S., Belevich, I., Jokitalo, E., Schorb, M., Klemm, A., Tischer, C., 2022. FEBS Lett</a>
</li>
<li>
Reproducible image handling and analysis. <a href="https://www.embopress.org/doi/full/10.15252/embj.2020105889">Miura K NS. EMBO J. 2021;40(3):e105889.</a>
</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>images</category>
  <category>how-to</category>
  <category>cheat sheets</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_cheatsheets/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_cheatsheets/SchmiedJambor_Figure4.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="111" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Summer23</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Summer23/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>A few sketches I made in summer 2023 in Smilka, Plön, Beverbeck, Berlin.</p>
<div class="{=html}">
<iframe src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/summer23/slideshow.html" frameborder="0" width="800" height="600">
Sketches
</iframe>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sketches</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Summer23/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Summer23/Scan1.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="102" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to… image availability</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_avail/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="how-to-image-availability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-to-image-availability">How to… image availability</h2>
<p>I <a href="../../posts/Image_how_mag/index.html">said this before</a>, but it should be said again: Make a copy of your original microscope/image file before starting any processing and adjustments and then store this image file along with the final, processed image somewhere save. In an ideal world your colleagues should see your final published image figure and be able to re-do the analysis to get there from a provided microscope image. Ideally, nobody would need to ask you, i.e., the files (TIFFimage, PNG image, scripts, method, anaylsis pipeline etc) should be in a public repository. At present, finding authors and working email adresses is a lot of detective work with changing affiliation, Email, or even profession. This was “wonderfully” demonstrated recently. Researchers investigated how well “data available upon request” really works. To no ones surprise and in almost 50%, this did not even got an Email replies. The team then made “rigorous attempts to contact the authors”, i.e.&nbsp;continuously bothered the authors, which increased the data availability a little, but not enough (Tedersoo et al., 2021).</p>
</section>
<section id="public-places-for-your-data" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="public-places-for-your-data">Public places for your data</h2>
<p>For regular light microscope image techniques many public storage possibilities exist and should be used. Free options for up to 20-50Gb of image data are <a href="https://zenodo.org/">Zenodo</a>, <a href="https://osf.io/">Open Science Framework</a>, and <a href="https://figshare.com/">Figshare</a>. These repositories are broad and allow upload of any kind of digital data. A dedicated option for image data are <a href="https://www.openmicroscopy.org/omero/institution/">OMERO servers</a>, however these are usually maintained by institutions, rarely by individual labs and can be both public or private. Image data repositories, that are fully searchable are still being build. The <a href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/bioimage-archive/">BioImage Archive</a> is one such attempt that accepts any image data, the Image Data Resource publishes image datasets that serves as reference datasets, and EMPIAR is a resource specifically for Electron Microscopy data.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_avail/Beth.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Overview of data repositories that accept images. From: <a href="https://zenodo.org/record/7628604">Beth Cimini, 2023</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="which-files-should-be-deposited" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="which-files-should-be-deposited">Which files should be deposited?</h2>
<p>The specific file type of the microscope image will depend on imaging setup. A standard format for loss-loss compression is TIFF or the open format OME-TIFF. In specialized microscopy techniques that rapidly accumulate tera-bites of data, e.g., long-term live-imaging, light-sheet microscopy, or similar the original microscopy files are often not stored locally and too large for public repositories. When only compressed files can be kept, PNG files are preferred to e.g., JPEG files, as they allow loss-less compression.</p>
<section id="read-more" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="read-more">Read more:</h4>
<p>The BioImage Archive - Building a Home for Life-Sciences Microscopy Data. 434, 167505. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2022.167505">Hartley et al 2022 J Mol Biol.</a></p>
<p>A call for public archives for biological image data. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-018-0195-8">Ellenberg et al 2018. Nat Methods.</a></p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>images</category>
  <category>how-to</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_avail/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_avail/Beth.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="67" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to… image colors</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_color/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="how-to-image-colors" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-to-image-colors">How to… image colors</h2>
<p>Images come in many appearances. Photos, histology staining, and some clinical image are usually not color adjusted and shown in full color. Electron microscopy images show one layer of information and are shown in greyscale. In light microscopy images we can excite features in several different wavelengths and combine them in multi-colored images. And this is where trouble starts (more on trouble <a href="../../posts/Image_numbers/index.html">in my overview</a>. I already wrote about <a href="../../posts/Image_how_annot/index.html">color annotation</a>, today I focus on the image colors.</p>
</section>
<section id="adjust-brightness-contrast" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adjust-brightness-contrast">Adjust brightness &amp; contrast</h2>
<p>For each channel, brightness and contrast can be adjusted separately. When images are to be compared, fixed intensity values should be used. Adjustment can be done in linear mode, which is applied uniformly to the whole image [note: if you are really into image display details there is much more to learn for you here, monitor display are not uniform, different algorithms are “linear” in different ways etc. If this is critical for your image analysis, learn more. If not, stop here and move on with your science].</p>
<div id="fig-adjust" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_color/Adjust_channel.png" height="400" class="figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: Adjust channel settings in light microscope images. from: Christopher Schmied, F1000R 2020.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="select-color-display" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="select-color-display">Select color display</h2>
<p>The vast majority of light microscope cameras capture each emission spectrum as a separate greyscale image. Users then often select a display color (‘lookup table’) for each channel. Many times users simply pick the color of the emission wavelengths. DAPI peaks at 461 nm and is then shown in blue, GFP peaks at 509 nm, which is in the green portion of the visible spectrum, and RFP peaks at 583 nm,hence is shown as red.</p>
<section id="visibiilty-of-colors" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visibiilty-of-colors">Visibiilty of colors</h4>
<p>The problem is that blue or red on the black background of microscopy images have a much lower visibility than the original greyscale image. We can see much more fine details when the signal is shown in white on black, as in the original greyscale image. You thus serve your audiences best if you show microscope images in greyscale also in your figures</p>
<div id="fig-visibilitly" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_color/Colors_visibility.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: Display colors of light microscope images and a visibility test (greyscale render): details are barely visible in blue on a black background, more structures can be seen when data is shown in white.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="accessibility-of-colors" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="accessibility-of-colors">Accessibility of colors</h4>
<p>When we prepare figures we should also consider color-blind audiences. Problems to differentiate red/green, as is the case in deuteranopia, is well known, but also other combinations may be problematic. Online software and also ImageJ allow you to test color combinations for their visibility to diverse audiences. In general: you may find possibilities to combine two channels in color-blind save mode. It is however impossible to find color options for three or more channels. Thus your safest option is again to show each color channel with a separate greyscale image.</p>
<div id="fig-colorcombo" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_color/Colors.png" height="400" class="figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;3: Think of accessibility of your colors and do a visibility test for color combinations.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="why-are-we-still-debating-color-choices" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-are-we-still-debating-color-choices">Why are we still debating color choices?</h2>
<p>In all forms of science communication, including image preparation, authors should be considered of colorblind readers. Among data scientists, it is well established for at least over a century that red and green colors should not be used in parallel when communicating data.</p>
<p>W.C. Brinton already wrote about this topic in his books in 1914 and 1939 (Chapter 49 “Color and its use”), citing an even older article by Edward Ayers from 1907, that “One man in twenty and one women in about two hundred are unable to see red and green normally” (Brintons book is <a href="https://archive.org/details/graphicpresentat00brinrich/mode/1up">available online</a>).</p>
<p>Surprisingly, being considerate with color choices still not reached all: a widely shared technology feature in Nature (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-021-02696-z">Katsnelson, 2021, Colour me better: fixing figures for colour blindness</a>) again calls for authors to use inclusive colors. Also this is echoed by many scientific societies e.g., <a href="https://www.ascb.org/science-news/how-to-make-scientific-figures-accessible-to-readers-with-color-blindness/">the American Society for Cell Biology</a>.</p>
<div id="fig-brinton" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_color/Brinton_book.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_color/Brinton_colorcombo.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;4: WC Brinton published in 1914 his book “Graphic presentation”, which included a guide to which color-combinations and their visibility to normal vision (right column) and color blind (left column) audiences .</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="more-on-color-combinations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="more-on-color-combinations">More on color combinations</h2>
<p>How exactly colors can be combined and still be accessible to all readers is controversial. For some images, such as colored photographs, rendering them safe for viewing by colorblind readers is not possible and risks sacrificing clarity. But, as pointed out above, adjusting the display colors is simple for most light microscopy images. Here, colors are selected in the microscope or image processing software. Many already offer combinations of color that are accessible to most colorblind audiences. Currently, many scientists already embraced green/magenta as a color scheme to replace green/red images. However, this may pose a semantic problem, when referring to red-fluorophores depicted in magenta color etc, or a convention problem to others, who feel “Green Fluorescent Protein” should not be shown in e.g., cyan. In light of these semantic and convention obstacles, scientists should embrace publishing each channel of a multicolored light microscope image as a standalone, separate (greyscale) image. Grayscale images are in any case superior to discern fine image details such as specific structures or cells in images. Human eyes perceive the contrast between light and dark areas more easily than they do contrast between a color and dark areas, e.g.&nbsp;as is the case when showing intensities in green on a dark background.</p>
</section>
<section id="literature-on-colors-in-microscopy" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="literature-on-colors-in-microscopy">Literature on colors in microscopy</h2>
<p>A Review of Color Blindness for Microscopists: Guidelines and Tools for Accommodating and Coping with Color Vision Deficiency.<br>
<a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S1431927615000173">Keene, D.R., 2015, Microscopy and Microanalysis</a></p>
<section id="tools-and-resources-for-color-choices" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tools-and-resources-for-color-choices">Tools and resources for color choices</h4>
<ul>
<li>
Design color palettes &amp; test accessibility<a href="https://hclwizard.org">HCLwizard</a>
</li>
<li>
Find color palettes for charts<a href="https://colorbrewer2.org">ColorBrewer2</a>
</li>
<li>
Blog on Viz for Colorblind readers<a href="https://www.datylon.com/blog/data-visualization-for-colorblind-readers">Datylon blog</a>
</li>
<li>
Tableau blog on red/green<a href="https://www.tableau.com/blog/examining-data-viz-rules-dont-use-red-green-together">Tableau blog</a>
</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>images</category>
  <category>how-to</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_color/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_color/Brinton_colorcombo.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="153" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to… image annotation</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="how-to-image-annotation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-to-image-annotation">How to… image annotation</h2>
<p>I already wrote <a href="../../posts/Image_numbers/index.html">why we need to annotate more</a>, <a href="../../posts/Image_how_mag/index.html">how to choose your image format</a>, and <a href="../../posts/Image_how_scale/index.html">how to annotate physical scales</a>. But we also have to annotate symbols, regions, stainings and fluorphores (for general colors <a href="../../posts/Image_how_color/index.html">wait for next post</a>.</p>
<div id="fig-good-bad" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/Annotations.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: Image annotations, the good, the bad and the ugly <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">from Jambor 2021</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="color-annotations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="color-annotations">Color annotations</h2>
<p>Image colors are usually annotated in the color they are shown, this is fast and easy for readers. Problems may arise when image colors are not color-bind save, when the image has yellow stainigs that do not work for text. Alternatively, the color name is written out and linked to the molecule (GFP = green, actin-Cy3 = red etc). In this case the readers has to do a semantic translation of color name to image color, which is slow and error-prone as we all see colors differently.</p>
<p>Whenever you have &gt;2-3 colors, you can safely assume that not all will be able to distinguish them any more. Not everyone is familiar with “lavender” or “salmon”, as we know since the hilarious and VERY <a href="https://blog.xkcd.com/2010/05/03/color-survey-results/">exhaustive survey by XKCD</a>.</p>
<div id="fig-xkcd" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 57.1%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/color_boy_girl2010-03-01-12bf011.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="400"></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 42.9%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/xkcd_satfaces_map_450.webp" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: His/Her color names by Doghouse Diaries and the color space with name-territoires by XKCD</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="visibility-of-annotations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visibility-of-annotations">Visibility of Annotations</h2>
<p>Just like your image colors, also your annotations should be color-blind save. But some color combinations are also hard to decipher with regular vision.</p>
<div id="fig-poorex" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/yellow_text_poor.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/yellow_text_Poor_visibility.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;3: ouch…</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="symbols-arrows-rois" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="symbols-arrows-rois">Symbols, arrows, ROIs</h2>
<p>Oftentimes lines, arrows, symbols and regions of interest (ROIs) are used to point out important details or areas in an image. It is essential that all annotations are distinguishable and clearly explained. Avoid using the same symbol for several meanings: if arrows are used to point out structures, they should not concurrently be used to also indicate motion.</p>
<div id="fig-exampleannot" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/Symbols_arrows_lettercode.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;4: Examples of annotations in scientific images</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="annotate-your-heart-out.." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="annotate-your-heart-out..">Annotate your heart out..</h2>
<p>Whatever you may feel important for your readers you should make an effort to help them take it in fast. Below are examples that annotate the position of laser manipulation with dashed-line ROI, color-code the z-stack depth, progressive zoom, and the overlap colors (good to be reminded in RGB space that mixing red, blue and green is WHITE).</p>
<div id="fig-many" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/Annotations_many.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;5: Examples of what can be annotated.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="many-annotations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="many-annotations">Many annotations</h2>
<p>If you went a bit overboard with your annotations, you may have to find creative solutions. Here are two examples:</p>
<div id="fig-manyA" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/Annotations_toomany.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/Full_page_scace_forAnnotations.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;6: Annotations, how much is too much? Some clever annotation <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">strategy for many labels</a> above, and a practical approach, make figures larger, here a full-page.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="consistent-code-from-image-to-quantification" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="consistent-code-from-image-to-quantification">Consistent code from image to quantification</h2>
<div id="fig-image-chart" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/ColorScheme_image-chart_annotation_good copy.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="200"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/Annotation_image-chart_good.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="550"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;7: A good example of consistent color (left) and label (right) between image and chart.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div id="fig-bad" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/ColorScheme__image-chart_annotation_poorvis_1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/ColorScheme__image-chart_annotation_poorvis_2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;8: Colored annotations are hard to see on multi-colored background - the link to the chart above is almost impossible to see (right).</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="annotate-where" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="annotate-where">Annotate where?</h2>
<p>Ideally the explanation is in the figure itself, as close to the data as possible. Alternatively, explanations can go to the figure legend. Remember however that at times the legend is not even on the same page as the figure, that legends may have word limits, and that a legends in which many annotations have to be explained become tedious to read.</p>
</section>
<section id="speaking-of..-figure-legends" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="speaking-of..-figure-legends">Speaking of.. Figure legends</h2>
<p>Figure legends are essential for complete image annotation. They should inform about the specimen, maybe preparation, dyes and all essentials for understanding the image. Which information is in the figure versus the figure legend (and method section) depends on journal requirements and personal preference, but in sum the information should make the figure self-explanatory. A critical analysis by Yu of figure legends showed that up to 70% of the information needed to comprehend the figure was lacking, many times readers needed a complete paper to fully comprehend figures.</p>
<section id="read-more" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="read-more">Read more</h4>
<p>Are figure legends sufficient? Evaluating the contribution of associated text to biomedical figure comprehension. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1747-5333-4-1">Yu, H., Agarwal, S., Johnston, M., Cohen, A., 2009. J Biomed Discov Collab</a></p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>images</category>
  <category>how-to</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_annot/Symbols_arrows_lettercode.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="66" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to… image scale information</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="how-to-image-scale-information" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-to-image-scale-information">How to… image scale information</h2>
<p>Microscopy images without any annotations are abstract art rather than scientific evidences. <a href="../../posts/Image_how_mag/index.html">After deciding on image size and format</a>, the next step towards making image content understandable is to annotate the object size, explain all colors, and any symbols used.</p>
</section>
<section id="scale-bars-in-publications" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="scale-bars-in-publications">Scale bars in publications</h2>
<p>Every scientific image needs scale information to allow audiences to compare and relate the image size with the physical world <a href="../../posts/Image_numbers/index.html">and not all published images currently have scale info</a>. Scale information is best conveyed with a scale bar with its physical dimensions. It’s also possible to make statements about the size of the entire image, or, as last resort, state the dimensions in the figure legend.</p>
<div id="fig-Scales" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/Scale_examples.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: Examples of poor and better scale information, <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">from Jambor 2021</a></figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="many-ways-to-show-scale-in-images" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="many-ways-to-show-scale-in-images">Many ways to show scale in images</h2>
<p>Scales are included in scientific illustrations for a long time in different ways. In Maria Merian times, size statements were included in the book, not the drawing itself; she usually stated in the preface that all drawings are at real scale.</p>
<p>Many times familiar objects are included in drawings or images for scale. Often, this is a human figure, e.g.&nbsp;with plants and trees, rocks, or animals.</p>
<div id="fig-humanscale" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/Scale_human.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="250"></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 42.7%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/ReDreaw_ipad.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="320"></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 24.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/NICE_scalebar_human-for-scale.PNG" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="180"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: Humans for scale of plants, dinosaurs, and unexpectedly large invertebrates</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>At times other familiar objects are included: a penny is placed on a rock in geology or a measuring tape is shown.</p>
<div id="fig-familiars" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/worms_copy.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/NigelLarkin_Nat_SCA_Scalebar.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;3: Earth worm next to measuring tape and bone scaled with credit-card measure (merch from Nat_SCA)</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="scales-in-microscopy-images" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="scales-in-microscopy-images">Scales in microscopy images</h2>
<p>Using familiar objects for scale isn’t possible when we make microscopic observations. This may be why in the earliest published photographs and microscope pictures (mind you, there aren’t many as images were considered a waste of space and decorational) scales are omitted.</p>
<p>A lovely tool that tried placing familiar objects next to microscopic scenes is the Utah genetics cellular scale animation <a href="http://learn.genetics.utah.edu/content/cells/scale/">Genetics Utah Animation of Scale</a> I never cease to be amazed at the relative size differences of cells and how they vary over so many magnitudes!</p>
<section id="alternative-to-scale-bars" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="alternative-to-scale-bars">Alternative to scale bars</h4>
<p>A cute alternative to the regular scale bar is here, thanks to Filip Port (<span class="citation" data-cites="crisprflydesign">@crisprflydesign</span><span class="citation" data-cites="fediscience.org">@fediscience.org</span>) who turned the googly eyes of <span class="citation" data-cites="thekengevik">@thekengevik</span> into a veritable scale bar!</p>
<div id="fig-googly" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/thekengevik_googlyeyes.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/Screenshot 2022-11-09 at 10.03.32.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;4: thekengevik googly eyes idea and googly eyes adapted for scale</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And finally, a fun but maybe not quite practical idea is suggested by Monica Zoppe, cats for scale! Check out <a href="http://www.nature.com/nmeth/journal/v14/n7/abs/nmeth.4300.html"> her article!</a></p>
<div id="fig-cat" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/Zoppe.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;5: Unconventional idea for annotating scales in biology</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="suggestions-for-making-scale-bars" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="suggestions-for-making-scale-bars">Suggestions for making scale bars</h2>
<p>As we don’t have a clear mental image of the size of a salt grain, sesames seed, or submicron cats to reliably use them to scale, we have to for now rely on scale bars. Using ImageJ/FIJI this can be rapidly accomplished: when using Bioformats to import microscopy files, the metadata, including the physical size, is read in. Then use Analyze &gt; Tools &gt; Scale Bar to define length, width, color, position, and label or your scale bar.</p>
<section id="length" class="level5">
<h5 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="length">Length</h5>
<p>Be kind to your audience and use simple units, such as 100um, 50um, 10 or 2um.</p>
</section>
<section id="color" class="level5">
<h5 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="color">Color</h5>
<p>Scale bars should have a high contrast with the background. Avoid red, green, or blue bars, as these colors might be considered part of the image.</p>
</section>
<section id="position" class="level5">
<h5 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="position">Position</h5>
<p>Lower left corner is a safe place. The upper space should be kept for important information like species, cell type, or gene name, and many times figure panel name (A, B,…).</p>
</section>
<section id="add-scale-bar-last" class="level5">
<h5 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="add-scale-bar-last">Add scale bar last</h5>
<p>In the process of writing your manuscript you may re-think the figure size. Also images are re-sized for posters and slides. It is therefore easiest to add only a very fine scale bar with FIJI and then re-draw it in Adobe Illustrator (or PowerPoint, as I now that about half of you out there use PowerPoint for making figures and posters!).</p>
</section>
<section id="in-fijiimagej" class="level5">
<h5 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="in-fijiimagej">In FIJI/ImageJ</h5>
<div id="fig-fiji" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/FIJI_scalebar_figure_2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;6: Quick scale bar with FIJI/ImageJ. Also check this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UBcipUjwFec&amp;list=PL8jDF_fSen2BxniT30JZ4zzZfQi4AHni9&amp;index=4">Youtube Tutorial from Lipke Lab</a></figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="ps" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ps">PS</h4>
<p>…if you find old scientific images with scale bars, or interesting scales, send them my way for my collection!</p>
<p>Here are some first returns:</p>
<div id="fig-examples" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/Scale_human_geology.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="350"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/scale_Bar_legendproblem.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="270"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;7: Human for scale in geology (courtesy James Saenz) and: pick useful scale bar units, 17:4is NOT user friendly (courtesy Jerome Mutterer).</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Oh and over at Reddit there seems to be a whole community making <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/BananasForScale/">Banana’s for scale</a> a thing, as Barry Rowlingson <span class="citation" data-cites="geospacedman">@geospacedman</span><span class="citation" data-cites="mastodon.social">@mastodon.social</span> pointed out. One example adapted for biology by Hauke Drechsler (<span class="citation" data-cites="HD_sci">@HD_sci</span><span class="citation" data-cites="biologists.social">@biologists.social</span>):</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/HaukeDrechsel_banana_for_scale.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure 8: Why not! (joke)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>images</category>
  <category>how-to</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_scale/worms_copy.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="33" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to… image formatting</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_mag/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="how-to-image-formatting" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-to-image-formatting">How to… image formatting</h2>
<p>In my <a href="../../posts/Image_numbers/index.html">previous post</a> I wrote about issues that make images in publications hard to understand. Now let’s improve this!</p>
<section id="before-you-start" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="before-you-start">Before you start…</h4>
<p>At best do not mess with the image from your microscope (usually .TIFF).Before adjusting an image for publication, first make a copy and keep the original untouched somewhere save. You more likely than not will need it at some point, e.g.&nbsp;to re-do analysis with newer software, make a better version for publication, or to give to colleagues for reanalysis!</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="adjust-brighness-and-orientation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adjust-brighness-and-orientation">Adjust brighness and orientation</h2>
<p>Almost always adjustments are necessary in digital images, most common of the brightness and contrast. When doing quantitative comparisons of images, fixed intensity values should be used and novice users should only apply linear adjustments that are applied to the whole image. Important: make these adjustments before cropping an image! Miura and Norrelykke in detail describe how the same adjustment calculation varies when performed on an full-view versus a cropped image. Next, many images are rotated. There are consensus ways to orient images in many fields. Humans are shown with the head at the top and the feet at the bottom, but also other traditions exist, e.g.&nbsp;for epithelia the apical side in shown at the top etc. This often requires rotation of microscope images. All rotations must be done carefully as this process redistributes image intensity values. In most software, increments of 90 degrees pixels can be reordered rather than interpolated, which maintains the intensity distribution. (Find out more here: Miura &amp; Norrelykke 2021, Schmied &amp; Jambor, 2020).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_mag/Kota.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Sequence matters when adjusting brightness contrast. Adapted from <a href="https://doi.org/10.15252/embj.2020105889">Miura &amp; Norrelykke</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="cropping-magnification" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cropping-magnification">Cropping &amp; Magnification</h2>
<p>Cropping is a normal adjustment to focus the audience on the key message. To show cellular structures, a close up of the organelle is required, not the whole slide that was imaged. As a rule, cropping is permitted, as long as no key feature is removed that is important for the scientific conclusion. Scientist should also consider the size of the image in the final figure: are the features that matter visible? Might it be better to show the image in larger size? Alternatively, consider enlarging and cropping the image to focus the reader on your key result, or ideally show the original image and an image detail (inset) side by side. When insets are shown their position in the original image must be indicated, e.g., with a “Region of interest”.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_mag/Insets.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Example of poor and improved insets in figures<a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">from Jambor 2021</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="assembling-a-figure-with-images" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="assembling-a-figure-with-images">Assembling a figure with images</h2>
<p>Finally, when images are all processed there are many solutions to assembling multi-panel figures. Usually, figures do not only show one microscope image, but several views, split channels, merged images, or false-color quantifications. One is <a href="https://imagej.net/plugins/figurej">FigureJ</a>, a plugin for ImageJ/FIJI by Jerome Mutterer. Another possibility is QuickFigures, again for ImageJ by Mazo. And last, it is also possible to run image processing scripts in the vector graphics software Inkscape directly (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hdlnZMybf7g">here</a> is a youtube tutorial by Jerome Mutterer).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_mag/FigureJ.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">FigureJ workflow to assemble a composite image figure</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="read-more" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="read-more">Read more</h4>
<ul>
<li>
Reproducible image handling and analysis. <a href="https://doi.org/10.15252/embj.2020105889"> Miura, K., Norrelykke, S.F., 2021. EMBO J</a>
</li>
<li>
Effective image visualization for publications - a workflow using open access tools and concepts.<a href="https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.27140.2">Schmied, C., Jambor, H.K., 2020. F1000Res 9, 1373.</a>
</li>
<li>
QuickFigures: a tool to quickly transform microscope images into quality figures.<a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0240280">Mazo, G., 2020. PLoS One</a>
</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>images</category>
  <category>how-to</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_mag/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_how_mag/Kota.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="58" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Many papers, many images, many problems</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_numbers/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="many-papers-many-images-many-problems" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="many-papers-many-images-many-problems">Many papers, many images, many problems</h2>
<p>500 papers are newly indexed in PubMed every day, almost 1 million each year (<a href="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/bsd/index_stats_comp.html">PubMed Statistics</a>). Many of these contain images: 20% have a photos, light or electron microscopy images, x-rays or similar (see <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7888968">Lee, 2018</a>). These images document the appearance or structure of specimen, tissues, or cells, and are a analysed to gain quantitative insights of biological processes.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_numbers/ImageTypes.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Image types</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="what-we-did" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-we-did">What we did</h2>
<p>Not too long ago a motivated group of scientists including me systematically analyzed the clarity and legibility of images (<a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">Jambor et al., 2021</a>). It turns out, in only a fraction of the publications, 10-20%, images are fully accessible and interpretable. To get to this number, we surveyed the image quality in the top journals, based on impact factor, in three representative fields, physiology, cell biology and plant sciences. We used a validated protocol and each article was assessed by two independent reviewers. The screening protocol covered diverse aspects: the image presentation in the figure, the completeness of feature annotations, presence of scale information, accessible image colors, and informative image titles/legends.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_numbers/Summary.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Example images showing the types of problems that were encounterd and their frequency. E.g., scale bars are missing in 45-70% of publicartions with images."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Summary of Image Survey, <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">from Jambor et al., 2021</a>)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="scale-information-missing-in-up-to-70-of-papers" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="scale-information-missing-in-up-to-70-of-papers">Scale information: missing in up to 70% of papers</h4>
<p>This is possibly the most unexpected finding: many images in publications lack sufficient information about physical scales. This is unexpected as each of us had some memories of being taught about scale bars early in our careers, if not already in high-school biology. Scale information can come in many forms and all of them were acceptable to us: as scale bar inside the image, as information about the physical size of the entire image in figures, and even an indication of the magnification were deemed acceptable. This however was entirely missing in 10-30% of the papers and incomplete in another 30-40%.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_numbers/Scale_numbers.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Many papers omit scale information for images, <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">from Jambor 2021</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_numbers/Scale_examples.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Examples of poor and better scale information, <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">from Jambor 2021</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="colors-often-not-accessible-to-color-blind" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="colors-often-not-accessible-to-color-blind">Colors: often not accessible to color blind</h4>
<p>Red/Green color blindness affects around 10% of the male population, and less than 1% of the female population. Nonetheless, astonishingly 30 - 50% of the screened images were not color blind friendly! In addition, in around 20% of images the annotations of colors were not color blind save. This means that colorblind readers are hindered in seeing or fully understand the key scientific messages conveyed in these images.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_numbers/Colors.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Colors in microscope images and visibility tests <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">from Jambor et al., 2021</a>)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_numbers/Colors_visibility.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Examples of color visibility <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">from Jambor et al., 2021</a>)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="details-not-visible-or-insets-not-explained" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="details-not-visible-or-insets-not-explained">Details: not visible, or insets not explained</h4>
<p>Just like in photography, also in microscopy the key subject should ideally fill the frame. What does this mean? If you want to show a cellular detail, do not show the entire petri dish of cells – cutting unnecessary image details is allowed, if this does not change the conclusion! Likewise, if you aim to show morphology of an organ, make sure that said organ is fully visible – image stitching, if declared (legend, methods), is possible and allowed. Many times an overview, e.g.&nbsp;of cell culture dish and a focus on some detail is shown with two images side by side, one the original image and alongside this a zoomed inset. In one third of publications, likely accidental, the origin of the inset in the original image is not clearly indicated or entirely missing. This hinders the audiences to understand the relation of inset to image, especially since in half of the cases the inset is also not explained in the legend.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_numbers/Insets_numbers.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Inset example and the number of missing inset explanations <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">from Jambor et al., 2021</a>)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="annotations-incomplete" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="annotations-incomplete">Annotations: incomplete</h4>
<p>Speaking of annotations – they are not optional, despite what the data suggest: up to 30% of publications omit an explanation of the colors shown in images (e.g., channel, staining), up to 40% fail to explain symbols, regions of interest, or arrows, and many times the species or cell type visible in the image is not clear from the legend. Especially all colors and symbols must essentially be explained with the figure, while further details such as specimen could also be described in the method section – alas, it is also missing very often in this section, but that is another story (Marques G, 2020; Sheen et al., 2019).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_numbers/Annotations.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Poor and better annotations, here of the color channels <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">from Jambor et al., 2021</a>)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="a-happy-ending" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-happy-ending">A happy ending</h4>
<p>We showed that across all criteria, only 1/5 th of publications with images show fully interpretable images. Beyond our analysis, many papers also fail to understandably present data on image acquisition, imaging methods and also image processing details. We as scientific community have to ensure that our scientific data is truthful and reliable, and also understandable to current and future readers. Incomprehensible images limit effective science communication and we should strive to improve all data we present in publications.</p>
I have compiled a series of blog posts “How to… Publish Images” that provide a rapid guidance and links to further resources.
<ul>
<li>
How to… image formatting (August 1) <a href="../../posts/Image_how_mag/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
How to… image scale information (August 3) <a href="../../posts/Image_how_scale/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
How to… image annotation (August 8) <a href="../../posts/Image_how_annot/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
How to… image colors (August 10) <a href="../../posts/Image_how_color/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
How to… image availability (August 15) <a href="../../posts/Image_how_avail/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
Cheat sheets for image publishing (August 21) <a href="../../posts/Image_cheatsheets/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
A short history of science images (August 27) <a href="../../posts/Image_history/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
How to… image analysis (Sept 20) <a href="../../posts/Image_how_analysis/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
<li>
How to… avoid misleading with images (Sept 22) <a href="../../posts/Image_misleading/index.html">Link to blog</a>
</li>
</ul>
<p>PS if you are interested, I usually write about more general visualizations, e.g., <a href="../../posts/GraphicalAbstract_1/index.html">How to create Graphical Abstracts</a></p>
</section>
<section id="read-more" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="read-more">Read more</h4>
<ul>
<li>
Our article assessing the current quality of images and Recommendations for Creating clear and informative image-based figures for scientific publications. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">Jambor, H., Antonietti, A., Alicea, B., Audisio, T.L., Auer, S., Bhardwaj, V., Burgess, S.J., Ferling, I., Gazda, M.A., Hoeppner, L.H., Ilangovan, V., Lo, H., Olson, M., Mohamed, S.Y., Sarabipour, S., Varma, A., Walavalkar, K., Wissink, E.M., Weissgerber, T.L., 2021. PLoS Biol</a>
</li>
<li>
A study quantifying how many images are in publications. Viziometrics: Analyzing Visual Information in the Scientific Literature.<a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7888968">Lee P IEEE Transactions on Big Data 2018;4:117-29.</a>
</li>
<li>
Imaging methods are vastly underreported in biomedical research.<a href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.55133">Marques G, P.T., Sanders MA, 2020. Elife 2020.<br>
</a>
</li>
<li>
A big Replication Study that also includes image data: Biomechanical remodeling of the microenvironment by stromal caveolin-1 favors tumor invasion and metastasis.<a href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.45120">Sheen, M.R., Fields, J.L., Northan, B., Lacoste, J., Ang, L.-H., Fiering, S., Reproducibility Project: Cancer Biology, 2019. eLife 8, e45120.</a>
</li>


</ul></section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>images</category>
  <category>how-to</category>
  <category>cheat sheets</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_numbers/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/Image_numbers/Summary.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="50" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to… Graphical Abstracts 3: The final touch</title>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helena Jambor</dc:creator>
  <link>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/GraphicalAbstracts.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="paper-alert-this-is-now-published-in-plos-computational-biology" class="level5">
<h5 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="paper-alert-this-is-now-published-in-plos-computational-biology">Paper Alert: this is now published in <a href="https://dx.plos.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011789">PLOS Computational Biology!</a></h5>
</section>
<section id="how-to-graphical-abstacts-3" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-to-graphical-abstacts-3">How to… Graphical Abstacts 3</h2>
<p>I described tools and icon resources in <a href="../../posts/GraphicalAbstract_1/index.html">Graphical Abstracts 1</a> and how to organise the page for a legible graphical abstract in <a href="../../posts/GraphicalAbstracts_2/index.html">Graphical Abstracts 2</a>. Now, as the last step, we can add a little text where necessary, quicker orient readers with colors, and make sure we got it right with a little feedback.</p>
<section id="text" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="text">Text</h4>
<p>A minimum amount of text will be necessary in almost all Graphical Abstracts: to explain arrows, images, and point to conclusions. Of course, keep text to a minimum and understandable, i.e., without jargon or abbreviations. Use easy to understand language: you may want to use popular keywords or phrases to rapidly grab attention and orient audiences. Text may have to be added to label pictograms that are otherwise ambiguous or that are uncommon. A circle could mean molecule, area, cell or similar. <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/text1.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Pictograms with unclear meaning"></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/text2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Pictograms explained with minimal text</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>When no images are available, e.g., for highly specialized words, text can be used as a substitute for images.</p>
<p>Think of all text as legends to your visuals! In this spirit, try to encode your text annotations the same way as the visual element they are encoding.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/text3.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Colored text to explain key point - saving your files</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/text4.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Multi-colored text as legend to entire graphical abstract</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="colors" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="colors">Colors</h4>
<p>We first and foremost make graphical abstracts as a visual appetizer for our readers, and as such they should be attractive and colorful. In all visualizations we use color to highlight or contrast (see also examples with text above), to depict the natural appearance of a visualized object, or to encode numbers: sequential/continuous data should be encoded with varying saturation of one color, diverging data with a 2-color scheme, and qualitative data may be encoded with varying color hues</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/Colors-01.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Color use in visaualizations.Rabbit by Albrecht Dürer, Public domain, via Wikimedia Commons.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="consistent-colors" class="level5">
<h5 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="consistent-colors">Consistent colors</h5>
<p>In all cases it is important to use colors consistently. The color code/color scheme should be maintained within the abstract and also between abstract and the main manuscript. A change in color is considered to also be a change in meaning – colors should therefore be carefully chosen. As colors are perceived immediately, they should overall be used sparsely to not overload readers and distract from the main message.</p>
</section>
<section id="accessible-colors" class="level5">
<h5 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="accessible-colors">Accessible colors</h5>
<p>When selecting colors, authors should always ensure that colors are accessible to all readers, including color blind audiences. We included many color suggestions in <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001161">our big survey of image figures published in PLOS Bio</a>: <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/ColorVisibility.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Color visibilities on backdrop"></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/Colorblind.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="440"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Colors as seen by color-blind audiences</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And, the importance of making all your figure accessible to color biond was was prominently highlighted in a technology feature by Alla Katsnelson in <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-02696-z">Nature</a>, featuring also my humble opinion.</p>
</section>
<section id="tools-for-selecting-colors-and-color-schemes" class="level5">
<h5 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tools-for-selecting-colors-and-color-schemes">Tools for selecting colors and color schemes:</h5>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://colorbrewer2.org/">ColorBrewer</a> was developed for data color schemes in maps, but is easy to use and works perfectly well for other sciences need to visualize data. <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/ColorBrewer.png" class="img-fluid"></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://paletton.com/">Paletton</a> lets you choose attractive color combinations using a color wheel, e.g.&nbsp;adjacent colors for harmonious appearance or complementary colors to contrast scenarios. <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/P.png" class="img-fluid"></p></li>
</ul>
<p>Neat: with palettton you can try out your color combination in a mock website/poster, in an art-work similar to a graphical abstract scenario, and also check how color combinations are visible to color-blind audiences:</p>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/P_poster-website.png" class="img-fluid" width="220"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/P_flowerdesign.png" class="img-fluid" width="220"> <img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/P_colorblind.png" class="img-fluid" width="260"></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://icolorpalette.com/color-palette-from-images">IColorpalette</a> let’s you pick a color scheme based on your favorite art work! Here’s one for all of us longing for some holiday!</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/holiday_colors.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Color scheme based on holiday picture, colors as hex values"> Bonus: you can download the SVG file and directly use the colors via the color pipette!</p>


</section>
</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>datavis</category>
  <category>Graphical abstracts</category>
  <category>how-to</category>
  <guid>https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/GraphicalAbstracts.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jun 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://helenajamborwrites.netlify.app/posts/GraphicalAbstracts_3/text3.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="54" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
